Atmosphere
and
climate.
Earth's
atmosphere
has
no
definite
boundary,
gradually
becoming
thinner
and
fading
into
outer
space.
Three-quarters
of
the
atmosphere's
mass
is
contained
within
the
first
eleven
kilometers
(six
point
eight
miles)
of
the
surface;
this
lowest
layer
is
called
the
troposphere.
Energy
from
the
Sun
heats
this
layer,
and
the
surface
below,
causing
expansion
of
the
air.
This
lower-density
air
then
rises
and
is
replaced
by
cooler,
higher-density
air.
The
result
is
atmospheric
circulation
that
drives
the
weather
and
climate
through
redistribution
of
thermal
energy.
The
atmosphere
is
composed
of
seventy
eight
point
zero
eight
four
percent
nitrogen,
twenty
point
nine
four
six
percent
oxygen,
zero
point
nine
three
four
percent
argon,
and
trace
amounts
of
carbon
dioxide
and
other
gaseous
molecules.
Water
vapor
content
varies
between
zero
point
one
percent
and
four
percent
but
averages
about
one
percent.
Earth's
biosphere
has
significantly
altered
its
atmosphere.
Oxygenic
photosynthesis
evolved
two
point
seven
Gya,
forming
the
primarily
nitrogen–oxygen
atmosphere
of
today.
This
change
enabled
the
proliferation
of
aerobic
organisms
and,
indirectly,
the
formation
of
the
ozone
layer
due
to
the
subsequent
conversion
of
atmospheric
O
two
into
O
three.
The
ozone
layer
blocks
ultraviolet
solar
radiation,
permitting
life
on
land.
Other
atmospheric
functions
important
to
life
include
transporting
water
vapor,
providing
useful
gases,
causing
small
meteors
to
burn
up
before
they
strike
the
surface,
and
moderating
temperature.
This
last
phenomenon
is
the
greenhouse
effect:
trace
molecules
within
the
atmosphere
serve
to
capture
thermal
energy
emitted
from
the
surface,
thereby
raising
the
average
temperature.
Water
vapor,
carbon
dioxide,
methane,
nitrous
oxide,
and
ozone
are
the
primary
greenhouse
gases
in
the
atmosphere.
Without
this
heat-retention
effect,
the
average
surface
temperature
would
be
−18
degree
C
(−0.
four
degrees
Fahrenheit),
in
contrast
to
the
current
plus
fifteen
degree
C
(fifty
nine
degrees
Fahrenheit),
and
life
on
Earth
probably
would
not
exist
in
its
current
form.